Effective presenters not only think about their words, not only pay attention to their physical presence and their vocal emphasis,
they also pay attention to their audience, because really inspiring presenters will respond to what’s happening in the moment in the room.
That ability to make an emotional connection is the third crucial element of style that brings your message alive.
So what are some of the ways you can connect emotionally with an audience?
First of all, look at them. Look them in the eye.
Whether it’s a big audience or a small audience, make contact.
Now, if you’re speaking to a convention with a thousand people in the room, of course you can’t make eye contact with all of them.
But make eye contact with some individuals at the front. Let your gaze linger, and then move on.
And also, just anything you can do verbally to express empathy.
A simple thing like, “Okay, I know we’re all looking forward to lunch, but I just need you to concentrate for another 20 minutes.”
Expressing empathy gets people on your side.
Also, any time you open up a topic, tell people what you understand about how they feel about that topic now.
So: “We’re going to talk about cost now. I know this is a painful topic. Nobody likes talking about it,
but I really appreciate that you’ve given me some focused ideas to move forward with.
And before we start, are there any thoughts you have, or concerns you have, about how we’re doing this?”
So really kicking things off by putting them in the centre — that will build an emotional connection
with your audience, or the people you’re in a meeting with. The other, deeper point is really about your ultimate state.
Are you going into that meeting in an open state, with confidence and authenticity?
If you are, people will connect with that. Always remember that any presentation, at its best, is a dialogue.
That’s why the C of EPIC is conversation. It isn’t one-way communication. It’s two-way.
And the starting point for that is the emotional connection you forge with the audience. Build your empathy with the audience,
because if you don’t have empathy for them, they’re not going to connect with you.